<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rants | Grant Cohoe]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.grantcohoe.com/blog/categories/rants/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.grantcohoe.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-24T11:32:28-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.grantcohoe.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Grant Cohoe]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Facebook Friend Guidelines]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.grantcohoe.com/blog/2013/01/03/facebook-friend-guidelines/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-03T00:42:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.grantcohoe.com/blog/2013/01/03/facebook-friend-guidelines</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If I am the requester or the requestee, it means that I have had a conversation with you (Not chat/texted. Actual person-to-person) on at least two separate occasions. (Occasionally this may be reduced to one depending on circumstances) Do not get this confused with what I consider a "dialog". A dialog is nothing more than "Hi! How are you today? What's up?". A conversation entails we discussed and compared our thoughts on at least one topic at length >5min. Also If you are from my present, it means that I consider there a statistically significant chance that we will see each other in person again in the future. If you are from my past, then we talked at least twice on several (>2) occasions. If you are from my future, well that feature hasn't been implemented yet and will probably cause me to segfault.</p>

<p>The logic behind these guidelines is relatively simple. There is no substitute for real life interaction. The idea of "meeting someone over Facebook" doesn't sit well with me. Whenever I see a person friend-request someone they don't really know or have had any degree of conversation with, it makes me question their ability to do so face-to-face. It also helps avoid the potential "stalker" effect that can come about easily with social media.</p>

<p>Take for example Jack and Jill. Jack is an avid fan of a school sports team. Jill is his favorite player on the sports team. Jack and Jill do not know each other, and have had nothing more than a dialog (as defined earlier) between them at various meet-n-greet events. Jill gets a friend-request from Jack several days later. Jill not wanting to potentially upset Jack accepts the friend-request. She now encounters frequent chat messages from Jack that lead a quick and dull conversation. Various other actions get Jack labeled as a "stalker" in Jills mind. This is not where Jack wanted to end up as he is now considered "the bad guy". While his motives (assume everything here to be at face-value, no hidden agendas) are honorable, they have led to an awkward situation for both of them.</p>

<p>By my guidelines, Jill should never have accepted the friend-request. Similarly Jack should have never sent one. Since neither of them have had any level of in-person conversations, they have no common ground on which to establish a friendship.</p>

<p>I will occasionally receive friend-requests from people from High School. These I find myself subjecting to a higher degree of scrutiny since I do not associate with this crowd a whole lot anymore. If I did not particularly enjoy your presence back then, I probably have no reason to change that.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fix Me Maybe]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.grantcohoe.com/blog/2013/01/03/fix-me-maybe/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-03T00:23:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.grantcohoe.com/blog/2013/01/03/fix-me-maybe</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Fix Me Maybe (parody of Call Me Maybe)
Words by Grant Cohoe (cohoe)
Music &amp; original words by Carly Rae Jepsen</p>

<p>This was dedicated to Ross Delinger (rossdylan) because: "FIX THE DAMN IRC SERVER!" Like the original song, it then went a lot further than expected. What more might come of this?!</p>

<p><a href="http://csh.rit.edu/~ducker/fixmemaybe.mp3">MP3 - Sung by Alex Howland (ducker)</a></p>

<p>Lyrics:
```
I started as a project
Something come Fall we'd forget
The system full of neglect
But now you've logged into me.</p>

<p>Everything's been broke for awhile
It's not great R-T-P style
This wasn't supposed to be a trial
But now you've logged into me.</p>

<p>Your session was open
Bytes of logs were flowin'
Files were c-h-ownin'
Need to get them daemons going</p>

<p>I'm used to broken things
These users are crazy
But here's my address,
so fix me maybe?</p>

<p>It's hard to figure out
What is wrong here
But here's my address,
so fix me maybe?</p>

<p>I'm used to broken things
These users are crazy
But here's my address,
so fix me maybe?</p>

<p>And all the other boys
Try and break me
But here's my address,
so fix me maybe?</p>

<p>You took your time with fix
Broke in no time 'cause they're pricks
You didn't help anything
But still, you're logged in me</p>

<p>I page, and cache and write
Every morn day and night
Processor cycles aren't tight
But still, you're logged in me</p>

<p>Your session was open
Bytes of logs were flowin'
Files were c-h-ownin'
Need to get them daemons going</p>

<p>I'm used to broken things
These users are crazy
But here's my address,
so fix me maybe?</p>

<p>It's hard to figure out
What is wrong here
But here's my address,
so fix me maybe?</p>

<p>I'm used to broken things
These users are crazy
But here's my address,
so fix me maybe?</p>

<p>And all the other boys
Try and break me
But here's my address,
so fix me maybe?</p>

<p>Before you came into my logs
I was broken so bad
I was broken so bad
I was broken so so bad</p>

<p>Before you came into my logs
I was broken so bad
And you should know that
I was broken so bad</p>

<p>It's hard to figure out
What is wrong here
But here's my address,
so fix me maybe?</p>

<p>I'm used to broken things
These users are crazy
But here's my address,
so fix me maybe?</p>

<p>And all the other boys
Try and break me
But here's my address,
so fix me maybe?</p>

<p>Before you came into my logs
I was broken so bad
I was broken so bad
I was broken so so bad</p>

<p>Before you came into my logs
I was broken so bad
And you should know that</p>

<p>So fix me, maybe?
```</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
